Hello. My name is Robert Smallshire.
Welcome to the seventh module of the
Advanced Python course. There's no doubt
that metaclasses can be difficult to
understand and reason about. Fortunately,
Python supports an alternative, which is
sufficient for many cases where we want to
customize classes at the point they are
defined. This alternative is the class
decorator. It's worth bearing in mind that
anything that can be achieved with a class
decorator can also be achieved with a
metaclass, although the reverse is not
true. In other words, class decorators are
less powerful than metaclasses, although
they are much easier to understand, so
should be preferred whenever the desired
effect can be achieved with either a
metaclass or a class decorator. Class
decorators work in much the same way as
function decorators. They apply a
transformation to a class after the class
definition body has been processed, but
before the definition is bound to the name
of the class. Let's start with a very
simple temperature class, which is
decorated with a function,
my_class_decorator. Set aside for the
moment that these getter and setter
methods are hardly the most Pythonic
solution, they'll serve our purpose for
the time being. To understand how class
decorators work, my class decorator is a
very simple function, which simply
iterates over and prints the attributes of
the class object. The class decorator must
accept the class object as its only
argument by a convention called cls, and
must return the modified class object or
an alternative class object, which will be
bound to the class name given in the
definition, in this case, Temperature.
When we import our module into a REPL
session we can see that the decorator is
executed when the temperature class is
first defined, which is when the module is
first imported. The class attributes
discovered by our decorator are dunder
module, our get_kelvin and set_kelvin
methods, dunder init, dunder weakref, and
dunder dict. It's important for our
Temperature class to maintain an important
invariant of the universe in which we live
that temperatures cannot be lower than
absolute 0, which is 0 Kelvin. Rather than
require that every method of our class
individually honors this class invariant,
we'll use a class decorator to wrap every method in an invariant checking proxy.