To do this in a generic way we need to
provide a way of specifying the class
invariant to the class decorator. Recall
from our earlier work with function
decorators, in Python Beyond the Basics,
to do this we define a function accepting
the arguments we need, which in turn
returns a decorator. A predicate function
which describes the invariant will be
passed to a factory function, a class
decorator factory, if you will, which
creates the actual class decorator, which
processes the definition of the
temperature class. As the temperature
class is processed by the class decorator
each callable member of the class is
identified in turn. These are the methods
of the temperature class, and a function
decorator is applied to each method. When
invoked, the method decorators delegate to
the original predicate function to verify
the invariant. There's a lot going on
here, so let's look at the code. The
invariant function, which is, in effect, a
decorator factory, accepts a predicate
function, which is used to test the
invariant, and returns the
invariant_checking_class_decorator
function. The class decorator accepts the
class object as cls and builds a list of
method names by identifying the callable
attributes. Each method is then processed
by a function called
wrap_method_with_invariant_checking_proxy,
which creates a function decorator for
each method, which calls the method, and
then checks that the invariant predicate
still holds. Note that we must use setattr
to update the class namespace, rather than
manipulating the class dunderdict
directly, as the latter is not mutable. We
can now define our temperature class like
this, calling the invariant class
decorator function and passing to it our
not_below_absolute_zero predicate
function. Our predicate function is
defined as our free function,
not_below_absolute_zero, which simply
tests the _kelvin private attribute. The
predicate function necessarily directly
accesses the private attributes of the
temperature class. That's fine. The class
and the function are very closely related.
Creating non-negative temperatures works
as expected. Here we create a temperature
of 5 Kelvin, but an attempt to construct a
negative temperature, here we tried to
create a temperature of -1 Kelvin,
demonstrates that our class decorator has
successfully wrapped dunder init with the
function decorator which checks the
invariant. Likewise, the function
decorator successfully wraps set Kelvin.
After constructing a temperature of 42
Kelvin we tried to modify the temperature
to -1 Kelvin, and the runtime error is
raised. Before we get too excited, let's
see what happens if we introduce some
properties, defined using the property
decorator into our Temperature class.
We've added properties to get and set the
temperature in both Celsius and Farenheit.
We create a temperature of 42 Kelvin,
which is reported back to us by the
Celsius getter as about -231 Celsius. This
is fine. Now let's set the Celsius to
-100. That's fine because -100 Celsius is
well above absolute zero. This works
without a hitch, and the temperature is
reported back to us in Celsius accurately.
Now let's try to set a temperature of -300
Celsius, which is well below absolute 0.
At this point, we should have received a
runtime error, as -300 Celsius is less
than absolute 0 Kelvin; however, no
exception is raised, and the class
invariant has been violated. If we try to
get the Kelvin value via the get_kelvin
method we do indeed get an error, but this
is too late. Class invariant violations
should never be detected by non-mutating
getters or other query methods. A breach
in our defenses has permitted the object
to get into an invalid state. How is our invariant check being circumvented?