Recall that the property decorator
produces a descriptor, which wraps the
getter and setter methods, but because
descriptors aren't callable functions they
aren't being detected and wrapped by our
invariant checking function decorator. To
fix this we need to beef up our machinery
to detect and appropriately proxy these
descriptors. If we take a peek at
vars(Temperature) we can see that
Fahrenheit and Celsius correspond to
property objects. Ideally, we detect any
value in this mapping, which is a
descriptor, which is any object supporting
any of the dunder get, dunder set, or
dunder delete methods. Unfortunately for
us, in this case, descriptors are also
used for all the functions and methods for
reasons we won't even get into in this
advanced course, so they too would be
detected. Instead, we'll go for the
simpler approach of looking for instances
of property, how updated class decorator
factory function looks like this. After we
have detected the method names by looking
for callable attributes, we detect the
property names by looking for attributes
where the value is an instance of
property. We'll insert a new section into
the body of the class decorator itself to
search for and wrap any class attributes
which are properties. This delegates to a
new function called
wrap_property_with_invariant_checking_proxy.
This function retrieves the property from
the class, and passes it and the predicate
function, to the constructor of a new
class, InvariantCheckingPropertyProxy. We
use setattr to replace the property with
the proxy. The
InvariantCheckingPropertyProxy is itself a
descriptor, implementing dunder get,
dunder set, and dunder delete. The
initializer simply stores references to
the referent property and the predicate
function. The implementations of dunder
get, dunder set, and dunder delete forward
to the underlying referent property, and
then check that the class invariant of the
instance remains unviolated. A quick test
at the REPL shows that everything is
working as designed. We'll create a
Temperature of 42 Kelvin, try to use the
Celsius setter to set a temperature of
-300 Celsius, which results in a runtime
error, showing that our
InvariantCheckingPropertyProxy is working.
A temperature of 100 Fahrenheit is
admissible, and we can convert that to
Celsius. Everything seems to be working fine.