For a final demonstration we'll show that
we can chain class decorators just as we
can with function decorators. We've added
a second invariant to be maintained to
ensure that the temperature is below the
hypothetical value, absolute hot. You can
read more about this on Wikipedia if
you're interested in the physics. At the
REPL we can see that both constraints are
enforced when we call instance methods,
such as set to Kelvin. We start with a
temperature of 37. 5 Kelvin, we're
prevented from setting a negative Kelvin
value, and if we try to set a Kelvin value
larger than absolute hot, 1 * 10 to the
33, the attempted invariant violation is
detected. Our class decorator has no
problem decorating the already decorated
methods on its second implication. The
proxy and properties are another story
though. Although the lower bound check
works as before on the properties, when we
try to set the temperature of -300 the
violation is detected. Attempts to violate
on the upper bound are not detected, so
setting a temperature of 1 * 10 to the 34
Celsius doesn't fail as it should. The
problem here is that our class decorator
is detecting specifically property
instances with the is instance check;
however, our invariant checking and
property proxy is not a property, so our
proxy which enforces the
not_below_absolute_0 invariant is applied
to the genuine property, although the
below_absolute_hot proxy is not applied to
the invariant checking and property proxy.
For a solution to this problem we'll use
Python's abstract base class mechanism, a
topic we'll explore in the next module of this course.