Let's start with a simple class to
represent two-dimensional vectors called
simply, vector. This has an initializer,
which accepts the two components of the
vector, x and y, and these are stored on
two instance attributes also called x and
y. We also include a dunder wrapper, so
that we can print a nice textural
representation of our vector objects.
Let's instantiate an object of this class
in the REPL with components 5 and 3. In
the list returned by the built-in dir
function we see two named attributes, x
and y, along with many of Python's special
dunder attributes, quite a few of which
we've explained previously in Python
Fundamentals of Python Beyond the Basics.
One attribute in particular is of interest
to us today, and that is dunder dict.
Let's see what this is. As its name
indicates, dunder dict is indeed a
dictionary, one which contains the names
of our objects attributes as keys, and the
values of our objects attributes as, well,
values. Here's further proof, if any were
needed, that dunder dict is a Python
dictionary. We can retrieve the type of v.
dunder dict, which is dict. We can
retrieve attribute values directly from
dunder dict by indexing into the
dictionary with square brackets, just like
a normal dictionary because it is a normal
dictionary. We can even modify attribute
values through dunder dict. Going further,
we can even remove attributes entirely. As
you might by now suspect, we can also test
for their existence using the in operator,
and add new attributes into the
dictionary, and thereby into our object.
Although all of these direct queries and
manipulations of dunder dict are possible,
for the most part, you should prefer to
use the built-in functions getattr,
hasattr, delattr, and setattr. Direct
access to dunder dict does have legitimate
uses though, and it's essential to be
aware of it's existence and how and when
to use it for advanced Python programming.
Our vector class, like most vector
classes, has hard wired attributes called
x and y to store the two components of the
vector. Many problems, though, require us
to deal with vectors in different
coordinate systems within the same code or
perhaps it's just convenient to use a
different labeling scheme, such as u and v
instead of x and y in a particular
context. Let's see what we can come up
with. In this code we accept a double star
keywords args argument, which is received
into the coords dictionary, which we will
then use to update the entries in dunder
dict. Remember that dictionaries are
unordered, so there's no way to ensure
that the coordinates are stored in the
order they are specified as actual
function arguments. Our dunder repr
implementation must iterate over the
dictionary, sorting by key for
convenience. Our modified vector class
allows us to provide arbitrary coordinate
names. Here we set p to three and q to
seven. This is all very well, but our
coordinates are now essentially public
attributes of our vector objects. What if
we want our vector class to be an
immutable value type, so we provide values
to the constructor, which can't be
subsequently changed? Ordinarily we will
do this by prefixing our attributes with
an underscore to signal that they are
implementation details, and then provide a
property with only a getter to prevent
modification. In this case, though, we
don't know the attribute names in advance,
so we can't declare a property getter,
which must be named at class definition
time, not at object instantiation time.
We'll show how to work around this using
the special dunder getattr method, but
first let's change our dunder init method
to store data in private attributes and
add dunder repr to report them correctly.
In this version of the code we use a
dictionary comprehension to associate new
names with a prefix underscore with each
existing value and assign this to a new
dictionary called private_coords. This is
what we then use to update dunder dict. In
the dunder repr code we must remember to
strip the leading underscore when
displaying the representation, in this
case, by using string slicing to emit the
first character. We can construct and
represent vector instances just as before.
Here we use p=9 and q=3, but now the
attributes are stored in private
attributes called _p and _q. Because of
this we can no longer access Python
directly. It doesn't exist as an attribute.