What we'd like to do is to fake the
existence of p for read access, and to do
that we need to intercept attribute access
before the AttributeError is raised. To do
that we could use dunder getattr. Notice
that there are two very similarly named
methods, dunder getattr, and dunder
getattribute. The former is only called
when regular attribute lookup fails. The
latter is called for all attribute access,
irrespective of whether an attribute of
the requests name exists of not. For our
case, we'll be using dunder getattr to
intercept lookup failures. Here's our
vector definition, which incorporates
dunder getattr. We've just added a simple
stub that prints the attribute name. When
we request non-existent attributes the
name of the attribute is now printed. Here
we ask for p and it prints name = p, and
when we ask for q it prints name = q, but
when we request the name of an attribute
that does exist we simply get the
attribute value, indicating that dunder
getattr isn't being called in these cases.
Now we can modify dunder getattr to
prepend the underscore to the name, and
retrieve the underlying attribute for us.
At first sight, this appears to work just
fine. Now we can retrieve p and q, but
there's some serious problems lurking
here. The first is that we can still
assign to p and q. Here we set p to 13.
Remember that there wasn't really an
attribute called p, but Python has no
qualms about creating it for us on demand.
Worse, because we have unwittingly brought
p into existence, dunder getattr is no
longer invoked for requests for p, even
though our hidden attribute, _p, is still
there behind the scenes with a different
value. Currently, p has a value of 13, and _p has a value of 5.