Although dunder getattr works fine with
attributes we've carefully faked, such as
p, look what happens when we try to access
an attribute for which there is no fake
support, such as x. We get a runtime
error, maximum recursion depth exceeded
while calling a Python object. In other
words, we've got infinite recursion. This
happens because our request for attribute
x causes dunder getattr to look for an
attribute, _x, which doesn't exist. This
in turn invokes dunder getattr again to
look up attribute __x, which doesn't
exist, and so on recursively until the
Python interpreter exceeds its maximum
recursion depth and raises a runtime
error. To prevent this happening you might
be tempted to check for the existence of
the private attribute using hasattr, like
this, raising an AttributeError if the
private attribute can't be found.
Unfortunately, this doesn't work either,
since it turns out that hasattr also
ultimately calls dunder getattr in search
of the attribute. What we need to do is
directly check for the presence of our
attribute in dunder dict using the not in
operator. This now works as we would wish.
We can create a vector with components p=9
and q=14. We can display the vector, which
echoes those values back to us. We can
query individual components, such as p,
which is of course equal to nine, but when
we request x, which is not defined, an
AttributeError is raised, as we would
expect. In fact, attribute lookup in
Python follows a pretty complex procedure,
so instead of invoking that procedure
again, by calling getattr, we can just
directly return the attribute from dunder
dict. This also enables us to switch to
easier to ask forgiveness than permission,
EAFP style programming, rather than look
before you leap, LBYL style programming.
Now the code attempts to retrieve the
attribute with a private name directly
from dunder dict. If it's not there a
KeyError is raised, and in the except
KeyError block we convert that to an
AttributeError. Of course, the easier to
ask forgiveness than permission version
has exactly the same behavior as the look before you leap version.