Now let's look at customizing attribute
deletion. Deleting attributes is something
that is very rarely seen in Python,
although it is possible. Here, using a
vector, v, with components p=1 and q=2,
our vector class also allows us to remove
attributes by calling delattr. We rather
mischievously delete the _p attribute
using a call to delattr and the _q
attribute by using the built-in del
statement. This leaves us with a vector
with no components. Although a client is
unlikely to attempt this inadvertently, we
can prevent it by overriding dunder
delattr. In a similar manner to our dunder
setattr, our dunder delattr simply raises
an AttributeError with a message informing
the client that the operation is
forbidden. Here's how that code behaves
when trying to delete either public or
private attributes using a vector, v, with
components p=9 and q=12. Deleting q using
the del statement with v. q causes an AttributeError to be raised.