There is no requirement for us to store
attributes directly in dunder dict. Here's
an example of a subclass of vector called
ColoredVector that stores immutable red,
green, blue color along with the immutable
vector components. Internally we store the
red, green, blue channels in a list, which
is assigned to the attribute called color.
We override both dunder getattr and dunder
setattr to provide read and write access
to the color channels, being careful to
forward requests to the super class when
necessary. Here we create a ColoredVector
called cv with color components red, 23,
green, 44, blue, 238, and special
components p=9, and q=14. Our code allows
us to retrieve these attributes, red,
green, p, and q as if they were just
regular attributes, although the storage
mechanisms for the vector components and
the color components are quite different.
When we do dir(cv) we see _p and _q for
the vector components, and color for the
color components. There's a gremlin
lurking here though. Our dunder repr
implementation in the base class makes an
assumption, which is no longer valid. It
assumes all attributes are prefixed with
an underscore internally, and doesn't know
about color. This causes our dunder repr
to behave in unexpected ways. This is
surprisingly hard to fit elegantly without
the derived ColoredVector class knowing
too much about implementation details of
the vector base class. We believe it
should be possible to derive from a class
without knowing how it works. The base
class dunder repr makes assumptions about
the contents of its dunder dict, which it
cannot reasonably expect to be respected
by subclasses. As an exercise, we
recommend changing vector, so it stores
it's components in a dedicated dictionary
separate from dunder dict, although of
course, this dictionary itself will need
to be stored in dunder dict. Here's
another fix which works by duplicating and
modifying some of the logic in the base
class into an override of dunder repr.
This method override works by removing the
attribute named color from the list of
keys before using the same logic as the
super class to produce the string of
sorted coordinates. The color channel
values are accessed in the normal way,
which will invoke dunder getattr. It's
worth bearing in mind that this example
demonstrates the awkwardness of inheriting
from classes, which were not deliberately
designed as base classes. Our code serves
its purpose in demonstrating customized
attribute access, but we couldn't
recommend such a use of inheritance in production code.