Do you remember the vars built-in
function? Without an argument it returns a
dictionary containing the current
namespace, and so acts just like the
locals built-in function, however, if we
supply an argument it returns the dunder
dict attribute of its argument, so instead
of writing obj. dunder dict we can write
vars(obj). Arguably, this is more Pythonic
than accessing dunder dict directly, for
much the same reason that calling
len(collection) is definitely more
idiomatic than calling collection. dunder
len. That said, the length returned by len
is always immutable, whereas dunder dict
is a mutable dictionary. In our opinion,
it's much clearer that the internal stage
of an object is being modified when we
directly modify the dunder dict attribute
like this by assigning to one of its keys,
then when we go via vars. Whichever form
you use, and we don't feel strongly either
way, you should be aware of this use of vars with an argument.