Now let's look at dunder getattribute as
opposed to dunder getattr. Recall that
dunder getattr is called only in cases
when normal attribute lookup fails. It's
our last chance for us to intervene before
the Python runtime raises an attribute
error, but what if we want to intercept
all attribute access? In this case, we can
override dunder getattribute. I use the
term override advisedly because it's the
implementation of dunder getattribute in
the ultimate base class object that is
responsible for normal lookup behavior,
including calling dunder getattr. This
level of control is seldom required, and
you should always consider whether dunder
getattr is sufficient for your needs. That
said, dunder getattribute does have its
uses. Consider this class, which
implements a logging proxy, which logs
every attribute retrieval made against the
target objects supplied to the
constructor. Since dunder getattribute
intercepts all attribute access through
the dot operator we must be very careful
never to access attributes of the logging
proxy through the dot. In the initializer
we use the dunder setattr implementation
inherited from the object super class to
do our work. Inside dunder getattribute
itself we retrieve the attribute called
target using a call to the super class
implementation of dunder getattribute,
which remember, implements the default
lookup behavior. Once we have a reference
to the target class we delegate to the
getattr built-in function. If attribute
lookup on the target fails we then raise
an attribute error with an informative
message. Note how careful we must be even
to return our object's dunder class. If
attribute retrieval was successful we
report as much before returning the
attribute value. Let's see this in action.
Note we're doing this in the regular
Python REPL in a terminal rather than
using the PyCharm REPL simply because
PyCharm itself performs a great many
invocations of dunder getattribute in its
console to support code completion. We
create a ColoredVector called CV with
colors red 23, green 44, blue 238, and
vector components p=9 and q=14. We then
wrap a LoggingProxy called CW around the
ColoredVector, CV. When we retrieve the p
attribute from CloudWatch our dunder
getattribute code is invoked, and the
message is printed. Likewise, for the red
attribute. So far so good, but what
happens when we write to an attribute
through the proxy? In this example both
writes appear to be accepted without
error, although only one of them should
be. Remember, the vector component should
be immutable. Only the colors are mutable.
In fact, though, neither of the writes
succeeded. Let's check by retrieving the
attributes. It looked like p was set to
19, but it still has the value 9. The
color red should have been set to 5, but
it still has the value 23. What's
happening here is that our attribute
writes to the CW proxy are invoking the
inherited dunder setattr on the object
base class, which is actually creating new
attributes in the logging proxy instances,
dunder dict, however, reads through the
proxy, correctly bypass this dunder dict,
and are redirected to the target. In
effect, the proxy dunder dict has become
write only. The solution to this is to
override dunder setattr on the
loggingproxy too. In the implementation we
retrieve the attribute called target using
a call to the superclass implementation of
dunder getattribute. We'll then use the
setattr built-in function to set the
attribute on the target. With dunder
setattr in place we can successfully write
through the logging proxy to modify
mutable attributes. Here we update red to
55, and attempted writes to immutable
attributes, such as p, are rejected as we intended.