Some special methods appear to bypass
dunder getattribute. Let's look at what's
going on. It's important to realize that
dunder getattribute only intercepts
attribute lookup through the dot operator.
Let's create a colored vector called cv
and a LoggingProxy for it called cw. If we
call the dunder repr method directly on
our proxy, cw, the call is routed via the
proxy, and is dispatched successfully on
the target, returning the repr for
ColoredVector. However, if we request the
repr of cw in the conventional manner
using the built-in function the dunder
getattribute function of our logging proxy
is not invoked. The call is not forwarded
to the ColoredVector, and instead we get
the default repr for the LoggingProxy
object. This demonstrates that dunder
getattribute can only be used to intercept
special method calls when the special
method is retrieved directly, which is
something we don't normally do. Normal
access to facilities provided by special
methods is through the built-in functions,
such as len, iter, and repr, and so on.
These all bypass the dunder getattribute
mechanism for performance reasons. What
this means in practice is that if you want
to write a proxy object, such as
LoggingProxy, which transparently proxies
an object, including its repr or other
special methods, it's up to you to provide
an implementation of dunder repr that
forwards the call appropriately. Here is
such a forwarding version of dunder repr.
It works by using dunder getattribute on
the object base class to retrieve the
target object, and then using getattr on
the target object to retrieve the dunder
repr method, which we then call. This now
works when called by the repr function,
although our proxy has become fairly
invisible at this point, which may hinder debugging.