One question you may have is, where are
the methods? Why is it that when we
introspect the dunder dict of an object we
only see attributes and not methods, but
as we have just seen with dunder repr, we
can retrieve methods using getattr, so
where are the methods? The answer is that
the methods are attributes of another
object, the class object associated with
our instance. As we already know, we can
get to the class object via the dunder
class attribute, and show enough it has a
dunder dict attribute, which contains
references to the callable objects, which
are the manifestations of the methods of
our class. Returning briefly to our vector
example, we create a vector, v, with
Vector components x=3 and y=7. When we
retrieve its dunder dict we see _y and _x
are private attributes. When we retrieve
v. dunder class we see the type of the
vector object, Vector. We can in turn
retrieve the dunder dict from dunder
class. This is an object of type
mappingproxy. Of course, we can retrieve
the callable object and pass that instance
to it taking the place of what is normally
the self-argument to a method. It's well
worth spending some time experimenting on
your own and poking around with these
special attributes to get a good sense of
how the Python object model hangs
together. It's worth noting that the
dunder dict attribute of a class object is
not a regular dict, but is instead of type
mappingproxy, a special mapping type used
internally in Python, which does not
support item assignment. To add an
attribute to a class you must use the
setattr function. The machinery of setattr
knows how to insert attributes into the class dictionary.