We'll finish off this part of the course
with a brief look at a mechanism in Python
for reducing memory use, slots. As we have
seen, each and every object stores it's
attributes in dictionary. Even an empty
Python dictionary is quite a hefty object
weighing in at 288 bytes. Here we create
an empty dictionary and use the getsizeof
function from the sys module to measure
its size. If you have thousands or
millions of objects this quickly adds up,
causing your programs to need megabytes or
gigabytes of memory. Given contemporary
computer architectures, this tends to lead
to reduced performance, as CPU caches can
hold relatively few objects. Techniques to
solve the higher memory usage of Python
programs can get pretty involved, such as
implementing Python objects in a lower
level language, such as C or C++, but
fortunately Python provides the slots
mechanism, which can provide some big wins
for low effort with tradeoffs that will be
acceptable in most cases. Let's take a
look. Consider the following class to
describe the type of electronic component
called a resistor. In our simple model
resistors have a resistance in ohms, a
tolerance in percent, and a power
capability in watts. We simply store these
as three instance attributes of the same
name. It's difficult to determine the size
in memory of Python objects, but with care
we can use the getsizeof function in the
sys module. To get the size of an instance
of resistor we need to account for the
size of the resistor object itself and the
size of its dict. Here we create a 10 ohm
resistor, r10, with a resistance of 10
ohms, a tolerance of 5%, and a power of 0.
25 of a watt. Its size weighs in at 152
bytes. Python objects being highly
dynamic, dictionary-based objects we can
add attributes to them at runtime and see
if this is reflected as an increased size.
Let's add a cost attribute to r10 of $0.
02. Now its size has shot up to 248 bytes.
This is quite a big object, especially
when you consider that the equivalent
struct in the C programming language would
weigh in at no more than 64 bytes with
very generous precision on the number
types. Let's see if we can improve on this
using slots. To use slots we must declare
a class attribute called dunder slots. To
dunder slots we assign a list containing
the strings, resistance_ohms,
tolerance_percent, and power_watts. Now
look at the space performance of this new
class. We can instantiate resistor, just
as before, and retrieve its attributes in
exactly the same way; however, its size is
much reduced from 152 bytes down to 64
bytes, less than half the size. There's
always a tradeoff though, as we can no
longer dynamically add attributes to
instances of resistor. This is because the
internal structure of resistor no longer
contains a dunder dict. For most
applications slots won't be required, and
you shouldn't use them unless measurements
indicate that they may help, as slots can
interact with other Python features and
diagnostic tools in surprising ways. In an
ideal world slots wouldn't be necessary,
and in our view they're quite an ugly
language feature, but at the same time,
we've worked on applications where the
simple addition of a dunder slots
attribute has made the difference between
the pleasure of programming in Python and
the pain of programming in a lower level,
but more efficient language. Use slots wisely.