Let's summarize what we've covered in this
course module. We've discovered that
Python objects store their attributes
internally within a dictionary called
dunder dict, which maps attribute names to
attribute values. We showed that instance
attributes can be created, retrieved,
updated, and deleted by direct
manipulation of dunder dict. We showed how
any failure to retrieve an attribute by
normal means causes the dunder getattr
special method to be invoked. The
implementation of dunder getattr can use
arbitrary logic to fake the existence of
attributes programmatically. Similarly,
assignment attributes can be customized by
overriding dunder setattr, and deletion of
attributes can be customized by overriding
dunder delattr. Calls to the hasattr
built-in function may also invoke dunder
getattr, so dunder getattr implementations
need to be particularly careful to avoid
non-terminating recursion. Occasionally,
it's necessary to customize all attribute
lookup, even for regular attributes. In
these cases, the default lookup machinery
and the special dunder getattribute method
of the object based class may be
overridden, taking care to delegate to the
base class implementation as necessary via
a call to super. Method callables are
stored in the dunder class. dunder dict
dictionary. Slots are a quick way to make
Python objects more memory efficient at
the cost of them being less dynamic. In
the next module we'll be looking at even
more sophisticated ways to customize
attribute access using a Python feature
called descriptors. Thanks for watching, and we'll see you in the next module.