Hello. My name is Robert Smallshire. In
this course module we'll be investigating
the abstract base class mechanism in
Python as originally defined in PEP 3119.
We previously used some abstract base
classes, such as Sequence from the
collections. abc module in our Python
Beyond the Basics course when implementing
a sorted set collection type. This time
we'll look at the tools provided in the
Python standard library ABC module for
creating abstract base classes of your own
design. If you're coming to Python from
another object oriented language, such as
Java, C++, or C# you may have preconceived
ideas of what an abstract base class is
and how to use one. Beware though, the
abstract base class mechanism in Python is
much more flexible and can work in what
may seem to be very surprising ways, so
pay attention. Thinking for a moment
beyond the confines of Python, what is, in
general, an abstract base class? The clue
is in the name. Base refers to the fact
that the class is intended to be the
target of an inheritance relationship.
That is, we expect another class to derive
from the base class. For instance,
GraphicalDevice here is intended as the
base class for other classes, such as our
EpsonWF3520PrinterDriver. Abstract refers
to the fact that the class cannot be
instantiated in isolation. That is, it
makes no sense to create an object of the
type of the base class alone. It only
makes sense to instantiate the class as
part of an object of a derived type.
Ideally, it should not be possible to
instantiate an abstract base class
directly. The opposite of abstract is
concrete, and in this example the
PrinterDriver is a concrete class, so it
makes sense to instantiate it. The
rational for any abstract base class is to
define an interface which derived classes
must implement. This allows client code to
be written against the base class
interface. In this example the
PrinterDriver must override the three
abstract methods of GraphicalDevice. Done
diligently, this leads to a highly
desirable property of class hierarchies
called Liskov Substitutability, a design
principle which states that subclasses,
from the point of view of the client code,
should be interchangeable. In other words,
client code developed against an abstract
interface should not require knowledge of
specific concrete types, only of the
capabilities as promised by the abstract
base class. For example, code written
against the interface of GraphicalDevice
should be able to render to an
EpsonWF3520Printer or a 1080p LcdDisplay
without modification. We can substitute
one concrete class for another. Abstract
base classes differ from pure interfaces,
such as those we have in languages like
Java, insofar as they can also contain
implementation code, which is to be shared
by all derived classes. Why do we need to
define named interfaces when we have duck
typing? Isn't it sufficient to know
whether a particular object responds to
the interface of a duck, and behaves like
a duck without actually knowing that it is
a duck? In Python this is true both in
theory and practice, but determining
whether a particular object supports the
required interface in advance of
exercising that interface can be quite
awkward. For example, what does it mean in
Python to be a MutableSequence? We know
that list is a MutableSequence, but we
can't assume that all mutable sequences
are lists. In fact, the MutableSequence
protocol requires at least 16 methods are
implemented. When relying on duck typing
it can be difficult to be sure that you've
met the requirements, and if clients do
need to determine whether a particular
object is admissible as a mutable sequence
with a look before you leap approach the
check is messy and awkward to perform robustly.