Abstract base classes in Python serve two
purposes. First of all, they provide a
mechanism for defining protocols or
interfaces, and ensuring the implementers
of those protocols meets some minimum
requirements. Secondly, they provide a
means for easily determining whether an
arbitrary class or instance meets the
requirements of a specific protocol. For
instance, after importing MutableSequence
from the collections. abc module. We can
determine that list is a MutableSequence
using the built-in, issubclass function.
This much may not be surprising, but let's
look at the base class of list. In fact,
we'll look at the transitive base classes
of list by examining its method resolution
order using the dunder mro attribute. This
reveals that list has only one base class,
object, and that MutableSequence is
nowhere to be seen. Further reflection, if
you'll excuse the pun, might lead you to
wonder how it is that such a fundamental
type as Python's list can be a subclass of
a type defined in a library module. We've
started out with this curious example, so
as to efficiently disabuse migrants from
other programming languages of any
existing notions of what abstract base
classes are, how they work, how they are
used, and why they are useful. That done,
we'll dig further into the mechanism.
Let's establish that MutableSequence is
indeed abstract by attempting to directly
instantiate it. This fails with a useful
type error explaining the five methods we
need to implement the MutableSequence
protocol. The reason we don't need to
implement all 16 is that 11 of them can be
implemented in terms of the other 5, and
the MutableSequence abstract base class
contains code to do exactly this. Note,
however, that these implementations may
not be the most efficient. Since they
can't exploit knowledge of the concrete
class, they must work entirely through the
interface of the abstract class. Now to
the question of how issubclass(list,
MutableSequence) returns true. What
happens is that when we call
issubclass(list, MutableSequence) the
built-in issubclass function checks for
the existence of a method called dunder
subclasscheck on the type of
MutableSequence, which is to say, on the
metaclass of MutableSequence, and if this
method is present it is called with the
subclass list as an argument.
Issubclass(list, MutableSequence) is
roughly equivalent to this code. It is up
to the metaclass of MutableSequence to
determine whether or not list is a
subclass of MutableSequence, rather than
list being required to know that
MutableSequence is one of its base
classes. This, in effect, allows list to
be a subclass of MutableSequence without
MutableSequence being a superclass of list
in the normal sense of being the target of
an inheritance relationship. We describe
such base classes as virtual base classes,
which has nothing at all to do with an
identically named concept in C++. The
dunder subclass check method on the
metaclass of the virtual base class can do
pretty much anything it likes to determine
whether it's argument is to be considered a subclass.