Consider the code in weapons. py. In this
module we've defined a Sword class with a
metaclass, SwordMeta. SwordMeta defines
the dunder subclasscheck method to check
for the existence of callable swipe and
sharpen attributes on the class. In this
situation Sword will play the role of a
virtual base class. A few simple tests at
the REPL confirm that BroadSword and
SamuraiSword are indeed considered
subclasses of Sword, even though there is
no explicit relationship through
inheritance, so BroadSword is a subclass
of Sword, SamuraiSword is a subclass of
Sword, but Rifle is not a subclass of
Sword. This isn't the whole story though,
as tests of instances rather than classes
using isinstance will return inconsistent
results. Here we create an instance of
SamuraiSword and try
isinstance(samurai_sword, Sword). This is
false. This is because the isinstance
machinery checks for the existence of the
dunder instancecheck method, which we have
not yet implemented. Let's do so now. Our
dunder instance check implementation
simply delegates to dunder subclasscheck,
which is called as a metamethod on the
actual class, cls. With this change in
place our call to isinstance produces a
result consistent with the result from
issubclass. This surprising technique is
used in Python for some of the collection
abstract base classes, including Sized,
which is used to indicate whether we can
determine the number of items in a
collection with the built-in len function.
Let's import Sized from collections. abc
and create a new collection called
SizedCollection, which just holds a simple
integer size. SizedCollection implements
dunder init to initialize the size, and
dunder len to retrieve the size via the
built-in len function. As you can see,
implementing a dunder len method is
sufficient to be considered a subclass of
the Sized abstract base class. It's worth
bearing in mind that our implementations
of dunder instancecheck and dunder
subclasscheck in SwordMeta are somewhat
naïve, as they make no attempt to check
the regular, non-virtual based classes of
the objects being tested, which could lead
to some surprising behavior. Bear in mind
that correctly overriding dunder
subclasscheck and dunder instancecheck on
your own metaclasses is difficult. Don't
worry though, we'll be presenting some more digestible alternatives shortly.