Overriding subclasscheck affords class
implementors a great deal of flexibility,
so much flexibility, in fact, that not
only should you not expect symmetry
between the superclass and subclass
relationships, you shouldn't expect
transitivity of the subclass relationship.
What this means is that if C is a subclass
of B, and B is a subclass of A it doesn't
necessarily follow that C is a subclass of
A. One glaring example from Python
revolves around the Hashable virtual base
class from collections. abc. Let's import
Hashable from collections. abc, and test
whether object is hashable. Yes it is. Now
let's test whether list is an object. Yes,
of course it is. Now let's test whether
the list is Hashable. No it is not, so
even though list is an object, an object
is a Hashable, we cannot say that list is
a Hashable. This occurs because list,
which remember is a mutable collection,
disables hashing by removing the special
dunder hash method, which would otherwise
be inherited from object, and which the
Hashable abstract base class checks for
through its dunder subclass check
implementation. Some further investigation
reveals that the list class sets the
dunder hash attribute to None. The
Hashable dunder subclasscheck
implementation checks for this eventuality
and uses it to signal None hashability.
This example is also interesting because
it demonstrates the fact that even the
ultimate base class object can be
considered a subclass of Hashable,
underlining the lack of symmetry between
superclass and subclass relationships in Python.