We've pointed out that implementing dunder
subclasscheck and dunder instancecheck
correctly can be awkward to get right.
Fortunately, the standard library provides
some support for implementing abstract
base classes in the ABC module, the abc
metaclass, along with some other useful
pieces of infrastructure, including the
ABC base class and the abstractmethod
decorator. We'll cover each of these in
detail now. The ABCMeta metaclass
implements reliable dunder subclasscheck
and dunder instancecheck methods, along
with some other handy capabilities we'll
come to shortly. We'll have our Sword
class use ABCMeta instead of SwordMeta,
which will allow us to dispose of
SwordMeta after we've cannibalized it.
Now, of course, ABCMeta doesn't know what
it means to be a sword, so the test that
was previously in SwordMeta dunder
subclasscheck needs to be relocated
elsewhere. The ABCMeta dunder
subclasscheck method calls the special
dunder subclasshook method on our actual
class to perform the test. In fact, all
Python objects have the dunder
subclasshook class method, which accepts
the potential subclass as its only
argument. We can see this by calling it on
object where it returns not implemented.
The method should return True, False, or
NotImplemented. For classes where dunder
subclasshook returns NotImplemented the
subclass test continues with the usual
mechanism of testing the non-virtual base
classes. Boolean values definitively
indicate whether the argument class is to
be considered a subclass of the base or
not. Let's try implementing dunder
subclasshook for our sword class with
pretty much the same definition we use for
dunder subclasscheck in SwordMeta
previously. This class method, in
conjunction with ABCMeta, is sufficient to
make our issubclass and isinstance tests
work as expected. SamuraiSword is a
subclass of Sword, Rifle is not a subclass
of Sword, and an instance of broad_sword is an instance of Sword.