It's also possible to directly register a
class as a virtual subclass with an
abstract base class whose metaclass is
ABCMeta using the register metamethod. For
example, let's create an abstract base
class Text, and register the built-in
type, str, as a virtual subclass. Notice
that the register metamethod returns the
class which was registered, a point we'll
return to in a moment. Now we can even
retrofit base classes to the built-in
types albeit virtual bases. Here we
demonstrate that the built-in str class is
now considered a subclass of our text
class defined at the REPL, and string
objects are instances of Text. Because the
register metamethod returns it's argument
we can even use it as a class decorator.
Let's register a class, Prose, as a virtual subclass of Text.