You need to take care when combining
virtual subclass registration with the
dunder subclasshook technique because the
results of dunder subclasshook takes
precedence over the subclass registry.
Returning true or false from dunder
subclasshook is taken as a definite
answer. If you also want registration to
be accounted for you should return
NotImplemented to indicate not sure. To
see this in action let's add a lightsaber,
which has no sharpen method, to our
example. This class won't satisfy the
dunder subclasshook test we defined in
Sword, but we still want it identified as
a virtual subclass of sort, so we've
registered it using the decorator form of
Sword. register. Even though we've
registered LightSaber with Sword the
subclass test returns false. To fix this
we need to ensure that dunder subclasshook
never returns false because doing so
causes the dunder subclass check
implementation in ABCMeta to skip the
check for registered subclasses. Instead,
in the case of a negative result we should
return NotImplemented. With this change in
place we should exploit shortcut
evaluation of the logical operators.
Subclass detection now works as expected
for implicitly detected subclasses,
explicitly registered subclasses, and
non-subclasses. Do bear in mind, though,
that this somewhat contrived example is
designed to demonstrate that you should
take care with subclass registration. How
useful is our virtual base class, Sword,
now? The answer is not very because being
an instance of Sword is no longer a useful
predicate for the object in question, as
we can't guarantee the presence of the
sharpen method, which was, if you'll
excuse the pun, the whole point of the sword.