Finally, we reach the aspect of Python's
abstract base classes, which most
immediately springs to mind when we talk
about abstract base classes in general,
the ability to declare abstract methods.
An abstract method is a method which is
declared, but which doesn't necessarily
have a useful definition. Abstract methods
must be overridden in derived concrete
classes, and the presence of an abstract
method will prevent its host class being
instantiated. Abstract methods should be
decorated with the abstractmethod
decorator, and their abstractness will
only be enforced if the metaclass of the
host class is ABCMeta. Let's add abstract
methods to our Sword abstract base class.
First, we need to import abstractmethod
from the ABC module. Python syntax
requires that we provide a body for each
method, so for swipe and parry we raise a
NotImplemented error, but for thrust we
provide a default behavior of printing,
thrusting. We'll take this opportunity to
remind you of the distinction between
NotImplemented and NotImplementedError.
NotImplemented is a value returnable from
predicate functions, which are unable to
make a determination of true or false. On
the other hand, NotImplementedError is an
exception type to be raised in place of
missing code. We'll also update dunder
subclasshook to match. If we now make
BroadSword a real subclass of Sword by
explicitly adding Sword to the list of
base classes we cannot instantiate
BroadSword, as it is still too abstract.
We get a TypeError, Can't instantiate
abstract class BroadSword with abstract
methods, parry and thrust. We must
implement all abstract methods for the
class to be considered concrete. Notice
that in thrust we call the implementation
provided in the abstract class using
super. Now we can successfully instantiate
BroadSword and call its methods. Note,
however, that the requirement to implement
abstract methods doesn't extend to virtual
subclasses, only to real subclasses. We
can still instantiate SamuraiSword
successfully, even though it doesn't implement all of the abstract methods.