What if you need to combine abstractmethod
with other decorators? The abstractmethod
decorator can be combined with the static
method, class method, and property
decorators, although care must be taken
that the abstract method is the innermost
decorator. For properties you can
independently mark the getters and setters
as abstract. Recall that properties are
implemented using descriptors. When
implementing your own descriptors you'll
need to do a little extra work to ensure
your descriptor plays nicely with
abstractmethod. Let's look now at how to
propagate abstractness through
descriptors. Any descriptors which are
implemented in terms of abstract methods
should identify themselves as abstract by
exposing a dunder isabstractmethod
attribute, which should evaluate to true.
Here in MyDataDescriptor, which inherits
from the ABC base class, we've declared
dunder get, dunder set, and dunder delete
as abstract methods. The dunder
isabstractmethod attribute can either be
implemented as a class attribute of the
descriptor class or can itself be
implemented as a property, as we have done
here. Implementing as a property is useful
in cases where abstractness needs to be
determined at runtime, as we'll see in an
example shortly. First, though, let's see
this in action with a very simple example.
We will define a class called
AbstractBaseClass, which inherits from
ABC. Within this class we'll define two
properties called abstract_property and
concrete_property using the appropriate
combinations of decorators. By querying
the descriptor objects created by the
property decorators we can inspect the
dunder isabstractmethod attribute of the
two properties and see that they have been
marked as abstract and none abstract or
concrete, as necessary. This happens
because the dunder isabstract method flag
is inspected by the ABCMeta implementation
when the metaclass creates the actual
class object, which hosts the property
descriptor. So much for the theory, let's see this in practice.