We rounded off the previous module of this
course on class decorators by building a
class decorator for checking class
invariants after every method call and
property access. This worked fine for both
methods and properties with a single
application of the decorator, but with
chained invariant decorators the checking
didn't work as planned for properties,
with only the innermost invariant taking
effect. Let's recap. Although the
innermost lower bound check works when we
try to assign a temperature of -300
Celsius through the Celsius setter,
violating the upper bound with a
temperature of 1*10 to the 34 Celsius is
not detected as we had hoped. The problem
here is that our class decorator is
detecting specifically property instances
with this fragment where we inspect each
attribute of the class being decorated and
check whether it is an instance of
property. Because our property wrappers of
type InvariantCheckingPropertyProxy are
not detected as instances of property,
they are not wrapped a second time, and
the invariant specified in the outermost
decorator is not enforced. We promised to
use abstract base classes to fix this
problem, so let's go. We'll introduce a
new abstract base class called
PropertyDataDescriptor, which inherits
from the ABC convenience class, and which
contains three abstract methods, which
define the data descriptor protocol,
dunder get, dunder set, and dunder delete.
PropertyDataDescriptor also includes the
abstract property, dunder isabstractmethod
for correct propagation of abstractness.
Note that because dunder isabstractmethod
needs to look like an abstract attribute
we have implemented it by applying the
abstract method and property decorators in
that order. Having defined an abstract
base class, we now need some subclasses.
The first will be a virtual subclass, the
built-in property class, which will
register with the base class by calling
PropertyDataDescriptor.
register(property). The second subclass
will be a real subclass. We'll modify our
existing property proxy,
InvariantCheckingPropertyProxy, to inherit
from PropertyDataDescriptor, which will
also require that we override the dunder
isabstractmethod property. In the
implementation of dunder isabstractmethod
we delegate the attribute of the same name
on the referent property, which we are
wrapping. Finally, we need to update the
search and wrap logic in invariant
checking class decorator to use the more
general test for instances of
PropertyDataDescriptor, rather than the
more specific test for just property. With
these changes in place, both invariants
are enforced on property writes. We'll
create a temperature of 42 Kelvin, then
attempt to modify the temperature through
the Celsius setter with a temperature of
-300 Celsius, which is below absolute
zero. This now fails as designed,
signaling a violation of the temperature
not below absolute zero invariant. Then we
test the other invariant by assigning a
temperature of 1*10 to the 34 through the
Celsius setter. This also fails as
designed, signaling a violation of the
temperature below absolute hot classing
variant. There's a lot going on in this
code with decorators, metaclasses,
abstract base classes, and descriptors,
and it may seem somewhat complicated. All
this complexity is well encapsulated in
the invariant class decorator, so take a
step back, and enjoy the simplicity of the client code in the temperature class.