In this module we've explained Python
system of abstract base classes, which is
somewhat more flexible than similar
concepts in other languages. In
particular, we covered how the behavior of
the built-in issubclass and isinstance
functions can be specialized for a base
class by defining the dunder subclasscheck
and dunder instancecheck methods on the
metaclass of that base class. Specialized
subclass checks allow us to centralize the
definition of what it means to be a
subclass by gathering look before you leap
protocol checks into one place. Any class
which implements the required protocol
will become at least a virtual subclass of
a virtual base class. The standard library
ABC module contains tools for assisting in
the definition of abstract base classes.
Most important amongst these tools is the
ABC metamethod class, which can be used as
the metaclass for abstract base classes.
Slightly more conveniently, you can simply
inherit from the ABC class, which has
ABCMeta as its metaclass. ABCMeta provides
default implementations of both dunder
subclasscheck and dunder instancecheck,
which support two means of identifying
subclasses, a special dunder subclasshook
class method on abstract base classes or a
registration method. Dunder subclasshook
accepts a candidate subclass as it's only
argument, and should return true or not
implemented. False should only be returned
if it is designed to disable subclass
registration. Passing any class, even a
built-in class to the register metamethod
of an abstract base class will register
the argument as a virtual subclass of the
base class. An abstractmethod decorator
can be used to prevent instantiation of
abstract classes, and require methods to
be marked as such to be overridden in
real, although not virtual, subclasses.
The abstractmethod decorator can be
combined with other decorators, such as
staticmethod, classmethod, and property,
but abstractmethod should always be the
innermost decorator. Descriptors should
propagate abstractness from underlying
methods by exposing the dunder
isabstractmethod attribute. Python is a
large and complicated language with many
moving parts. We find it remarkable that
much of this complexity is so well hidden
for the vast majority of the time in
Python. We hope in this course we've given
you deeper insight into some important
mechanisms in Python which, while a bit
trickier to understand, can deliver great
expressive power. You've now reached the
end of this course in Advanced Python, and
now is the time to take what you've
learned and apply these powerful
techniques in your work and play with
Python. If you'd like written material to
go along with this course you should check
out our Python Craftsman book series. The
books correspond to our Pluralsight
courses, which cover the core Python
language. The first book in the Craftsman
series, The Python Apprentice, corresponds
to our Python Fundamentals Pluralsight
course. The second book, The Python
Journeyman, corresponds to our Python
Beyond the Basics Pluralsight course. The
trilogy is completed by the The Python
Master, which corresponds to this Advanced
Python course. Pluralsight viewers can
follow the URLs shown below each book to
get them at a deep discount. If you'd like
to dig further into some advanced uses of
Python you might care to swing by our
Sixty North Blog, Good with Computers,
where we cover some very advanced topics,
such as integrating Python with C++ code
and implementing a sophisticated
functional programming technique called
transducers in Python. We'll doubtless be
back with more content for the
ever-growing Python language and library.
Please remember, though, that the most
important characteristic of Python is
that, above all else, it's great fun to
write Python software, so enjoy yourselves.