Hello. My name is Robert Smallshire.
Welcome to the fifth module of the
Advanced Python course. In this course
module we'll be taking a deep dive into
exactly what happens when we create a new
object. With this knowledge in hand we'll
be able to exercise fine control over
instance creation, which allows us to
customize Python objects in powerful ways.
So, what does happen when you create an
object? Consider this simple class which
models the coordinates on a chess board
consisting of a file letter from a to h
inclusive, and a rank number from one to
eight inclusive. The class implements an
immutable value type. The initializer
establishes the invariance, and the
property accessors prevent inadvertent
modification of the encapsulated data.
It's easy to think of dunder init as the
construct implementation, but let's look
closely at what happens when we create an
instance of chess coordinate by calling
the constructor. Here we create an
instance called white_queen at coordinate
(d, 4). We'll step in with the debugger,
pausing on the first line of dunder init.
This much should already be evident from
the signature of dunder init, which
accepts self as its first argument, but
the object referred to by self already
exists. That is to say, the object has
already been constructed, and the job of
dunder init really is just to initialize
the object. At this juncture our debugger
is having difficulty displaying the
uninitialized object because our dunder
repr implementation, quite reasonably,
expects that the object has been
initialized. However, we can add a watch
in the debugger for type self to see that
self already has the required type, and
self. dunder dict to see that the instance
dictionary is empty. As we continue to
step through the initializer we can watch
as the instance dictionary is populated by
assignments to attributes of self. Behind
the scenes, object. dunder setattr is
being called. Note also that dunder init
doesn't return anything. It simply mutates
the instance it has been given. So if
dunder init isn't responsible for creating
the instance, what is? If we look at the
special methods of ChessCoordinate using a
call to dir we can see one called dunder
new. We haven't defined dunder new
ourselves, but we do inherit an
implementation from the universal base
class object, so it is the base class
implementation of dunder new, which is
responsible for allocating our object in
this case. A simple test demonstrates that
ChessCoordinate. dunder new is in fact the
very same method as object. dunder new,
but what is the signature of dunder new?
Don't bother looking in the help because,
frankly, the answer isn't very helpful. We
have all the answers though, and we'll be overriding dunder new to demonstrate.