So let's figure out the signature of
dunder new. We'll implement the most basic
override of dunder new, which simply
delegates to the base class
implementation, although we'll add a few
print statements, so we can easily inspect
the arguments and return value. Notice
that dunder new appears to be implicitly a
class method. It accepts cls as its first
argument rather than self. In fact, dunder
new is especially cased static method that
happens to take the type of the class as
its first argument, but the distinction
isn't important here. The cls argument is
the class of the new object, which will be
allocated. In our case, that will be
ChessCoordinate, but in the presence of
inheritance it isn't necessarily the case
that the cls argument will be set to the
class in closing the dunder new
definition. In general, dunder new accepts
in addition whatever parameters have been
passed to the constructor. In this case,
we've soaked up any such arguments using
*args and ** keyword args, although we
could have used specific argument names
here, just as we have with dunder init.
We'll print these additional argument
values to the console. Remember that the
purpose of dunder new is to allocate a new
object. There's no special command for
that in Python. All object allocation must
be done by the dunder new implementation
on the ultimate base class object. Here,
rather than call the object. dunder new
implementation directly, we'll call it via
super. Should our immediate base class
change in future this is more
maintainable. The return value from the
call to object. dunder new is the new
instance of ChessCoordinate. We'll print
its id. Remember, we can't expect repr to
work yet, and then return. It is this
returned object that is then passed as the
self-argument to dunder init. We have
printed the id of self here in dunder init
to demonstrate that this is indeed the
case. We see that the id of obj in dunder
new is equal to the id of self in dunder
init, and also that the constructor
arguments have been forwarded to dunder new as expected.