Now let's look at customizing allocation
by overriding dunder new. We've shown the
mechanics of overriding dunder new. We
accept the class type and the constructor
arguments and return an instance of the
correct type. Ultimately, the only means
we have of creating new instances is by
calling object. dunder new. This is all
well and good, but what are some practical
uses? One use for controlling instance
creation is a technique called interning,
which can dramatically reduce memory
consumption. We'll demonstrate by
extending our program to allocate some
chess boards in the start of game
configuration. In our implementation each
board is represented as a dictionary
mapping the name of the piece to one of
our ChessCoordinate objects. For fun we've
used Unicode chess code points to
represent our pieces. In our program a
string comprised of white queen and white
rook means white queen's rook, and a
string composed of black king, black
bishop, black pawn means black king's
bishop's pawn. We need to be this specific
because, remember, dictionaries require
that keys are distinct. Our revised
program now has a starting board function
and main creates, for the time being, a
single search board. We've also removed
the various print statements from our
dunder new and dunder init functions. If
we create a single chess board this way a
peek in activity monitor on our Mac shows
that Python is allocated about 17. 1Mb of
memory. Creating 10, 000 chessboards
utilizes some 84. 2Mb of memory to store
the 320, 000 instances of ChessCoordinate
contained by the 10, 000 dictionaries that
must have been created to represent all
the boards. Bear in mind, though, that
there are only 64 distinct positions on a
chess board, and given that our
ChessCoordinate objects are deliberately
immutable value types, we should never
need more than 64 instances. In our
specific case, we should never need more
than the 32 positions occupied by the
pieces in their initial places. Let's put
in place updated definitions for dunder
new and dunder init, which achieve just
that. We're now using named position
arguments for the file and rank arguments
to dunder new, and we'll move the
validation logic from dunder init to
dunder new. Once the arguments are
validated we use them to create a single
tuple object from file and rank to use as
a key, and check if there is an entry
against this key tuple in a dictionary
called _interned we've attached as a class
attribute. Only if the tuple key is not
present in the dictionary do we allocate a
new instance by calling object. dunder
new. We then configure the new instance
during the remainder of the work that used
to be done in dunder init, and insert the
newly minted instance into the dictionary.
Of course, the instance we return is
whichever instance we have just or
previously inserted into the dictionary.
Our dunder init method is now empty and
can, in fact, be removed entirely. With
these changes in place allocating 10, 000
boards takes much less memory than
previously. In fact, we're down to 37.
1Mb, less than half what we required
previously. Remember that even though
we've interned the ChessCoordinate type we
still have to store 10, 000 distinct
dictionaries representing the board
configurations. Interning is a powerful
tool for managing memory usage. In fact,
Python uses it internally for integers and
strings, but it should only be used for
immutable value types, such as our
ChessCoordinate where instances can safely be shared between data structures.