We've covered a crucial topic in this
short course module, the distinction
between the allocation and initialization
of instances. We showed how the static
method, dunder new, is called to allocate
and return a new instance. It is
implicitly a static method, which accepts
the class of the new instance as its first
argument, and doesn't require either the
class method or static method decorators.
Ultimately, object. dunder new allocates
all instances. One use for overloading
dunder new is to support instance
interning, which can be useful when
certain values of immutable value types
are very common or when the domain of
values is small and finite, such as with
the squares of a chess board. This isn't
the whole story though, and Python offers
yet more control over instance creation at
the class level, although before we get to
that we need to understand meta classes.
Thanks for watching, and we'll see you in the next module.