Hello. My name is Robert Smallshire.
Welcome to the sixth module of the
Advanced Python course. We've mentioned
metaclasses several times. We owe you an
explanation. In this module we'll look at
the concept of the class of class of
objects, metaclass for short, the default
metaclass called type, specifying
metaclasses in class definitions, defining
metaclasses, including the special methods
of metaclasses, some practical examples of
metaclasses, which solve some problems
we've discovered earlier in the course,
and a look at how metaclasses interact
with inheritance. To assist us on our
journey to understand metaclasses we need
a simple class. We'll use Widget, which
will be empty. We'll instantiate some
widgets and introspect their types using
the type built-in function. We all know
that in Python the type of an instance is
its class, so what is the type of its
class? The type of a class is type. We've
covered this before in the introspection
module of Python Beyond the Basics, but it
bears repeating here. One potentially
confusing aspect here is that we're using
type as a function to determine the type
of an object, but type is also being used
as a value. It is the type of the class
object. However, this duality isn't so
unusual. We see exactly the same situation
with, say, list, where it is used as both
a constructor and the value. Here we use
the list constructor to construct a list
A, and the type of a is also list. Given
that the type of the Widget class is type,
we can say that the metaclass of a widget
is type. In general, the type of any class
object in Python is its metaclass, and the
default metaclass is type. Going even
further, we can discover that the type of
type is type. We can get the same results
by drilling down through the special
attribute, dunder class. Here's w. dunder
class, w. dunder class dunder class, and
w. dunder class dunder class dunder class,
which is the base of the recursion. To
understand where metaclasses fit into
Python we must consider how class objects
are created. When we define a class in a
Python source file like this, with class
Widget, this is actually shorthand for
class Widget with the object base class
and the type metaclass. In the same way
that the base class is implicitly object, the metaclass is implicitly type.