Roughly speaking, when we write a class
block in our Python source code it is
syntactic sugar for creating a dictionary.
The Python runtime populates the namespace
dictionary while reading the contents of
the class block, which is passed to a
metaclass to convert the dictionary into a
class object. To see how that works it's
important to understand the several tasks
that metaclasses perform during creation
of a new class. When we write class Widget
what's actually happening is something
like this, which is to say that the class
name is Widget, the metaclass is type, the
class has no base classes, other than the
implicit object, no keyword arguments were
passed to the metaclass, we'll cover what
this means later. The metaclasses, dunder
prepare method is called to create a new
namespace object, which behaves like a
dictionary. Behind the scenes the Python
runtime populates the namespace dictionary
while reading the contents of the class
block. The metaclasses dunder new method
is called to allocate the class object,
and finally, the metaclasses dunder init
is called to initialize the class object.
The name, bases, and namespace arguments
contain the information collected during
execution of the class definition,
normally the class attributes and method
definitions inside the class block,
although in our case, the class block is
logically empty. By providing our own
metaclass we can customize these
behaviors. We'll start with a very simple
metaclass called TracingMeta in a module,
tracing. py, which simply prints its
method invocations and return values to
the console for each of dunder prepare,
dunder new, and dunder init. Notice that
our metaclass should be a subclass of an
existing metaclass, so we'll subclass
type. Each of our overrides delegates to
the base class type method to do the
actual work required via a call to super.
Notice that although dunder new is
implicitly a class method, we must
explicitly decorate the dunder prepare
class method with the appropriate
decorator. Now we'll define a class
containing a simple method called action,
which just prints a message, and a single
class attribute, the answer, with the
cosmically inevitable value 42. We'll do
this at the REPL, so you can see clearly
when the metaclass machinery is invoked.
At the instant we complete the class
definition we can see from the tracing
output that Python executes the dunder
prepare, dunder new, and dunder init
method in turn. First of all, let's look
at dunder prepare, the purpose of which is
to produce an initial mapping object to
contain the class namespace. The mcs
argument, short for metaclass, is a
reference to the metaclass itself. This
first argument is analogous to the
self-argument passed to instance methods,
and the cls argument passed to class
methods. For metaclass methods it is
conventionally called mcs. The name
argument contains the name of our Widget
class as a string. The bases argument is
an empty tuple. We didn't declare any base
classes for widget, and the ultimate
object based class is implicit. The kwargs
argument is an empty dictionary. We'll
cover the significance of this shortly.
The most important aspect of dunder
prepare is that when it calls it's super
class implementation in type the return
value is a dictionary or, more generally,
a mapping type. In this case, it's a
regular, empty dictionary. This dictionary
will be the namespace associated with the
nascent class. Moving on to looking detail
at dunder new, the purpose of which is to
allocate the new class object, the mcs
argument is a reference to the metaclass
as before. The name and bases arguments
are still the string name of the new class
and the tuple of base classes. The mapping
object we returned from dunder prepare is
passed as the namespace argument to dunder
new. The Python runtime has populated this
dictionary with several entries, as it has
processed the class definition of widget.
Two of the items are our action method and
the the answer class attribute. The other
two items are dunder module and dunder
qualname, which the Python runtime has
added. The dunder module attribute is
mapped in the name of the module in which
the class was defined. Because we use the
REPL this is built-ins. The dunder
qualname attribute contains the fully
qualified name of the class, including
parent modules and packages. In this case,
it just contains the class name, as the
built-in's module used by the REPL is
available everywhere, being the last
namespace in the LEGB lookup hierarchy.
The kwargs dictionary passed to dunder new
is also still empty. Within dunder new we
delegate to the base class, type. dunder
new, via a call to super, forwarding the
mcs, name, bases, and namespace arguments.
The object returned by this call is the
new Widget class. We are in the process of
allocating and configuring. The new Widget
class is what we returned from dunder new.
Note that any changes we wish to make to
the contents of the namespace object must
have been made before this call, as this
is the point at which the class object is
created. To change the contents of the
class namespace after this call the class
object must be manipulated directly.
Finally, we come to dunder init, the
purpose of which is to configure the newly
created class object. Note that dunder
init here is an instance method of the
metaclass, not an explicit class method
like dunder prepare or an implicit class
method like dunder new. As such, it
accepts cls as its first argument, which
is one level less meta than cls. The name,
bases, namespace, and kwargs arguments are
all as before. Again, we delegate to the
type base class via super, although dunder
init doesn't return anything it's expected
to it's expected to modify the existing
class object that was handed to it. Note
that although the namespace object is
passed to dunder init, its content should
already have been used upstream by dunder
new when allocating the class object.
Changes to namespace will be ineffectual,
and any changes to the class object must
be affected by manipulating cls directly.
The key here is that metaclasses give us
the opportunity to modify the dictionary
of class attributes, which includes
methods, before the class is instantiated.
We even get the opportunity to modify the
list of base classes or produce an
entirely different class, if required,
although such uses are rare. We'll look at
some complex examples soon to make this
clear. You may be wondering which out of
dunder prepare, dunder new, and dunder
init you should override. If you don't
override dunder prepare the default
implementation in type will produce a
regular dictionary for the namespace
object, so you only need to override it if
you need the behavior provided by another
mapping type. Usually it will only be
necessary to override either dunder new or
dunder init, but of these two only dunder
new can make decisions before the new
class is allocated. The distinction
between dunder new and dunder init for
metaclasses is exactly the same as it is
for regular classes. Later we'll see that
it might be wise to prefer a configuration
in dunder init rather than dunder new, so that metaclasses are more composable.