Now let's look at a little known feature
of Python which allows us to pass
additional arguments to the metaclass.
Earlier we skipped over the fact that
dunder prepare, dunder new, and dunder
init can all support a kwargs parameter to
accept arbitrary keyword arguments. These
can be supplied in the parameter list when
defining a class, and any key with
arguments provided over and above the
named metaclass argument will be forwarded
to these three special methods. Here's an
example where we've passed a tension
keyword argument with a value of 496 in
the parameter list of our Reticulator
class definition, which uses TracingMeta
as its metaclass. As you can see, the
arguments are dutifully forwarded to the
metaclass methods, and the argument value
could have been used to configure the
class object. This allows the class
statement to be used as a kind of class
factory. Here's an interesting example,
which uses keyword args. The dunder new
method of the entries meta metaclass
expects kwargs to contain a num_entries
key, which maps to an integer value. This
is used to populate the namespace with
named entries using the letters of the
alphabet. At first sight it looks like we
only need to override dunder new to
achieve our aims. Let's try to use it.
We'll import EntriesMeta from entries, and
then define a new class, AtoZ, with
EntriesMeta as its metaclass, and passing
the custom argument, num_entries, as 26 to
get the 26 letters of the English
alphabet. The trace output shows that
num_entries 26 is successfully passed to
dunder new, but later we get an error from
dunder init. The problem we've set up
deliberately here is that both dunder new
and dunder init must accept any additional
keyword arguments. They must have the same
signature. We need a do nothing dunder
init to keep Python happy. Here it is.
With this important change in place
everything works as intended. We import
EntriesMeta, define AtoZ with EntriesMeta
and num_entries 26. We see the num_entries
item arriving keyword args, and we can see
the namespace object populated with all
the additional entries. Of course, we can
just use a regular argument, as well as or
instead of double star keyword args. Let's
convert num_entries into a proper
argument, in addition to double star
keyword args. This makes the code much
easier to understand, and still works exactly as before.