Now let's look at metaclass methods and
their visibility. We've covered three
important special methods for metaclasses;
dunder prepare, dunder new, and dunder
init, but what happens if we include other
methods in the metaclass? Let's see by
adding a method called metamethod to the
TracingMeta metaclass we were
experimenting with earlier. It accepts a
single argument, cls, which remember,
means it is an instance method of the
metaclass. Within it we simply print its
argument. Let's create the class widget
again with its TracingMeta metaclass. As
we complete our Widget class definition
the metaclasses are invoked. It turns out
that instance methods of the metaclass can
be accessed similarly to class methods of
the Widget class, and will have the
regular class passed to them as the first
and implicit argument. Here we call
metamethod directly on the Widget class.
However, unlike regular class methods we
create with the class method decorator, we
cannot access so called metamethods via
the Widget instance. Metamethods are
rarely used in practice, although one
metamethod in particular has an
interesting use, dunder call, which we'll
look at shortly. Class method definitions
in the regular class and its base classes
will take precedence over looking up a
method in its metaclass. Regular methods
of the metaclass accept cls as their first
argument. This makes sense because cls,
the class, is the instance of the
metaclass. It is analogous to self. On the
other hand, class methods of the metaclass
accept mcs as their first argument, the
metaclass, analogous to the cls argument of a class method in a regular class.