Now let's look at how to achieve very
fine-grained instantiation control by
overriding metaclass dunder call. For a
moment return your thoughts to the
material we covered in the previous module
of this course when we looked at instance
allocation with dunder new. We know that
in order to create instances we call the
constructor of the designed class. We have
learned that behind the scenes this will
call Widget. dunder new to allocate a
widget followed by Widgit. dunder init, to
do any further initialization. Let's pull
back the curtain, and see exactly what is
behind the scenes. The behavior of calling
dunder new followed by dunder init when we
call a constructor is actually the
responsibility of dunder call on the
metaclass. This makes sense when we
remember that dunder call is a metamethod,
and therefore can be called like a class
method, and that dunder call makes the
objects on which it is defined callable,
like functions. This is the mechanism by
which classes in Python become callable,
and what we have been referring hither to
as a constructor call is, in fact, the
dunder call metamethod. Let's see this in
action by overriding dunder call in our
TracingMeta example. Within dunder call we
print out its name and arguments, forward
the call with super to the type metaclass,
and then print out the return value from
the super class. We'll also implement a
TracingClass, which will use TracingMeta
as its metaclass. Tracing class overrides
dunder new and dunder init, so we can see
when they're called. Notice that when we
import the module into the REPL the
metaclass trifecta, dunder prepare, dunder
new, and dunder init are invoked when the
TracingClass is defined. Now we'll
instantiate TracingClass with a positional
argument and a keyword argument to its
constructor, 42 and keyword clef. Look
carefully at the control flow here. Our
call to the constructor invokes dunder
call on the metaclass, which receives the
arguments we passed to the constructor, in
addition to the type we're trying to
construct. Out dunder call override calls
the super class implementation, which is
type. dunder call in this case. See how
type. dunder call in turn calls
TracingClass. dunder new, followed by
TracingClass. dunder init. In other words,
it is type. dunder call, which
orchestrates the default class allocation
and initialization behavior. It is very
rare to see the dunder call metamethod
overridden. It's pretty low level in
Python terms, and provides some of the
most basic Python machinery. That said, it
can be powerful. In keywordmeta. py we
have an example of a metaclass overriding
dunder call, which prevents classes, which
use the metaclass, excepting positional
arguments to their constructors. In dunder
call we detect if args is non-empty, and
if that's the case we raise a type error.
We've also defined a regular class called
ConstrainedToKeywords, which uses
KeywordsOnlyMeta as its metaclass. Even
though the dunder init method in
ConstrainedToKeywords accepts positional
arguments through *args, execution never
gets this far, as non-empty positional
argument lists are intercepted by dunder
call in the KeywordsOnlyMeta metaclass,
which causes a type error to be raised.
Constructor calls which contain only
keyword arguments are permitted, as we
designed. We've covered a lot of the
theory and practice behind metaclasses.
Now well build on those ideas with some useful applications.