Python metaclasses can seem very, well,
meta, so it's time for a session on
metaclasses, which solve some actual
problems you've probably encountered. At
some point you've probably run into the
issue that duplicate class attribute names
aren't flagged by Python as errors. Here
we have a class, Dodgy, which contains two
definitions for method. In fact, the
second definition takes precedence because
it overwrites the first entry in the
namespace dictionary as the class
definition is processed. Let's write a
metaclass which detects and prevents this
unfortunate situation occurring. To do
this, rather than using a regular
dictionary as the namespace object used
during class construction, we need a
dictionary which raises an error when we
try to assign to an existing key. Here is
such a dictionary, OneShotDict, which is
implemented by specializing the built-in
dict type and overriding the dunder init
and dunder set item methods. Note that the
built-in dict has a quite sophisticated
initializer, which accepts many forms of
arguments, but something much simpler is
sufficient in our case. After calling the
super class dunder init the dunder init
implementation loops over any entries
which have been passed, inserting each key
and value pair in turn by call to dunder
setitem. In dunder setitem we check
whether the key is already in the
dictionary, and if it is we raise a value
error. Before we use the OneShotDict in a
metaclass let's just check that it's
working as expected. We'll create an
instance of OneShotDict called d, insert
the value 65 against the key A, insert the
value 66 against the key B, and then try
to insert the value 32 against the key A.
As hoped, the value error is triggered.
Now we can design a very simple metaclass,
which uses OneShotDict for the namespace
object called ProhibitDuplicatesMeta. All
we need to do is override the dunder
prepare class method, returning an
instance of our specialized dictionary.
Now if we try to define a class with
duplicate methods using this metaclass we
get an error. The main shortcoming here is
that the error message isn't hugely
informative. Unfortunately, we don't have
access to the part of the runtime machine,
which reads our class definition and
populates the dictionary, so we can't
intercept the ValueError and emit a more
useful error instead. The best we can do,
rather than using a general purpose
collection, like OneShotDict, is simply to
create a functional equivalent called
something like OneShotClassNamespace with
a more specific error message. This has
the benefit that we can pass in additional
diagnostic information, such as the name
of the class currently being defined into
the namespace object on construction,
which helps us produce a more useful
message. We adjust its initializer to
accept a positional name argument, which
we store as an instance attribute, _name.
In the guard clause of dunder set item we
change the exception type from value error
to type error, and edit the error message
to make it both more germane and more
informative. Lastly, we need to remember
to forward the class name, which is past
to dunder prepare, to the
OneShotClassNamespace constructor. When we
try to execute the module containing the
class with the duplicate method definition
we get a much more useful error message,
cannot reassign existing class attribute 'method' of 'Dodgy'. Much better.