For our next metaclass example let's
return to the Planet example we used in a
previous course module to illustrate
descriptors. Here's a reminder of the code
we ended up with. Recall that we
implemented a new descriptor type called
Positive, which would only emit positive
numeric values. This saved a lot of
boilerplate code in the definition of our
Planet class, but we lost an important
capability along the way because there is
no way for a descriptor instance to know
to which class attribute it has been
bound. One of the instances of positive is
bound to Planet. radius_metres, but it has
no way of knowing that. The default Python
machinery for processing class definitions
just doesn't set up that association. The
shortcoming is revealed when we trigger a
value error by trying to assign a
non-positive value to one of the
attributes. Here we try to give the planet
Mercury a nonsensical negative mass of
-10, 000. The error message doesn't, and
in fact, can't tell us which attribute
triggered the exception. Now we'll show
how we can modify the class creation
machinery by defining a metaclass which
can intervene in the process of defining
the Planet class in order to give each
descriptor instance the right name. We'll
start by introducing a new base class for
our descriptors called Named. This is very
simple and just has name as a public
instance attribute. The constructor
defines a default value of none because we
won't be in a position to assign the
attribute value until after the descriptor
object has been constructed. We'll modify
our existing positive descriptor, so it
becomes a subclass of named, and therefore
gains the name attribute. Again, the
constructor arguments define a default of
none. We've modified the argument listed,
dunder init, ensured that the super class
initializer is called, and made use of the
new name attribute in the error messages
raised by dunder set and dunder delete.
Now we need a metaclass which can detect
the presence of descriptors which are
named, and assign the class attribute
names to them. Here is
DescriptorNamingMeta. Again, this is
fairly straightforward. In dunder new we
iterate over the names and attributes in
the namespace dictionary, and if the
attribute is an instance of named we
assign the name of the current item to its
public name attribute. Having modified the
contents of the namespace we then call the
super class implementation of dunder new
to actually allocate the new class object.
The only change we need to make to our
Planet class is to refer to the metaclass
on the opening line. There's no need for
us to modify the uses of our positive
descriptor. The optional name argument
will default to none when the class
definition is first read before the
metaclass dunder new is invoked. By trying
to set a non-positive mass for the planet
Mercury we can see that each descriptor
object now knows the name of the attribute
to which it has been bound, so it can emit
a much more helpful diagnostic message,
such as Attribute value mass_kilograms
-10000 is not positive, allowing us to much more easily track down the problem.