We'll finish off this module by looking at
how metaclasses interact with inheritance.
Let's define two metaclasses, MetaA and
MetaB, related only by the fact that they
both subclass type. Both metaclasses will
be empty. We'll also define two regular
classes, A and B, which use MetaA and
MetaB as their respective subclasses. Now
we'll introduce a third class, D, which
derives from class A. Now let's introspect
class D itself, not an instance of D with
type D to determine what its metaclass is.
The metaclass of D is MetaA, which was
inherited from its regular base class A,
so metaclasses are inherited, but what
happens if we try to create a new class C,
which inherits from both regular classes A
and B with their different metaclasses,
MetaA and MetaB? Let's give it a go. When
we try to execute this code by importing
it at the REPL we get a type error with
the message, metaclass conflict: the
metaclass of a derived class must be a
(non-strict) subclass of the metaclasses
of all its bases. Python is telling us it
doesn't know what to do with the unrelated
metaclasses, MetaA and MetaB. Which
metaclass dunder new should be used to
allocate the class object? To resolve this
we need a single metaclass. Let's call it
MetaC, which we can create by inheriting
from both MetaA and MetaB. In the
definition of regular class C we must
override the metaclass to specify MetaC.
With these changes we can successfully
import C and check that its metaclass is
MetaC by asking for the type of C. So
we've persuaded Python to accept our code,
but our metaclasses are empty, so combine
trivially. Sometimes metaclasses will
combine in straightforward ways. For
example, our ProhibitDuplicatesMeta, which
overrides only dunder prepare, and our
KeywordsOnlyMeta, which overrides only
dunder call, can be combined into the
conceptually simple, but horribly named,
ProhibitDuplicatesAndKeywordsOnlyMeta,
which can have an empty class body, but
combine both behaviors. To cooperate
gracefully non-trivial metaclasses must be
designed with this in mind, which isn't
always straightforward or even possible if
the combination makes no sense. An
important step in designing cooperative
metaclasses is to diligently use super
when delegating to base classes because,
as we learned in Python Beyond the Basics,
super actually delegates to the next class
in the method resolution order or MRO,
which accounts for multiple inheritance.
Even though both our TracingMeta class we
defined earlier, and the
DescriptorNamingMeta metaclass we used
with the Planet attributes both override
dunder new, they combine easily in either
order because our implementations delegate
to the next class in the MRO chain using
calls to super. In planet. py we can
import TracingMeta, and combine our two
metaclasses into
TracingDescriptorNamingMeta with multiple
inheritance. The planet class definition
is executed when we import the module.
This is when the metaclasses do their
work, and we can see that tracing works as
expected. We can also confirm that the
descriptor naming is working by causing a
value error and checking for the
descriptor name in the error message. The
two metaclasses cooperate successfully by
using super. Another tip for designing
metaclasses which cooperate well is to
prefer to put code which configures the
class object in the dunder init
metamethod, which is handed the class
object to be configured rather than the
dunder new metamethod, which is
responsible for allocating the new class
object. Of course, each object may be only
allocated once, but could be configured
multiple times. Ultimately though, if
you're dependent on metaclasses from a
third party framework, such as SQLAlchemy
or Qt, there's a good chance their
metaclasses won't compose gracefully. You
should be able to figure out whether they
will compose by reading their source code if you have access to it.