We've covered a lot of ground in this
course module, and you should now know
more than the majority of Python
developers about the customization of
class creation using metaclasses. All
classes have a metaclass, which is the
type of the class object. The default type
of class objects is type. The metaclass is
responsible for processing the class
definition parsed from the source code
into a class object. The dunder prepare
metaclass method must return a mapping
object, which the Python runtime will
populate with the namespace items
collected from parsing and executing the
class definition. The dunder new metaclass
method must allocate and return a class
object and configure it using the contents
of the class namespace, the list of base
classes passed from the definition and any
additional keyword arguments passed from
the definition. The dunder init metaclass
can be used to further configure the class
object and must have the same signature as
dunder new. The dunder call metaclass
method, in effect, implements the
constructor for instances of the class,
and is invoked when we construct an
instance. An important use case for
metaclasses is to support so-called named
descriptors, whereby we can configure
descriptor objects, such as properties,
with the name of the class attribute to
which they are assigned. Strict rules
control how multiple metaclasses interact
in the presence of inheritance
relationships between the regular classes
which use them. Judicial metaclass design
using super to delegate via the MRO can
yield metaclasses which compose
gracefully. Thanks for watching, and we'll
see you in the next module where we'll
look at a simpler, but less capable
alternative to metaclasses for many uses, class decorators.