Hello. My name is Robert Smallshire.
Welcome to the fourth module of the
Advanced Python course. In this module
we'll investigate a feature of Python
you've been using, perhaps unknowingly,
called descriptors. Descriptors are the
mechanism used to implement properties in
Python. We covered properties thoroughly
in Python Beyond the Basics, but we'll
start here with a short recap. In Python
Beyond the Basics we showed how to create
properties using the property decorator.
In this module we'll dig deeper and show
how to create properties in the raw using
the property constructor. Then we'll show
how to create a specialized property by
defining a custom descriptor, which
implements the descriptor protocol. We'll
round off by demonstrating that there are
two categories of descriptor, data
descriptors and non-data descriptors, and
we'll show how these interact with
Python's somewhat complicated attribute
lookup rules. As promised, we'll start
with a very brief review of properties,
our entry point into the world of
descriptors. To explain descriptors we'll
be building this simple class to model
planets, such as Pluto here, focusing on
particular physical attributes, such as
size, mass, and temperature. Let's start
with this basic class definition for a
planet in planet. py consisting of little
more than an initializer. There are no
properties here yet. We'll add them in a
moment. Inside the planet initializer we
initialize the planet's name, its radius
in meters, its mass in kilograms, its
orbital period in seconds, and its surface
temperature in Kelvin. This Planet class
is simple enough to use. Here we create an
instance of planet called Pluto, which we
give a radius of 1184Km, together with the
correct values for its other physical
quantities. Of course, we can easily
retrieve the value of the radius_metres
attribute. Unfortunately, our code allows
us to represent nonsensical situations,
such as setting a negative radius, either
by directly mutating an attribute like
this, here we set the radius of Pluto to
-10, 000 meters or simply by passing
nonsense, such as a 0 mass and negative
orbital period or a temperature below
absolute 0 to the constructor. We already
know how to improve this sort of code, by
wrapping our instance attribute in
property getters and setters, which
perform validation by checking the
physical quantities are positive. We then
assigned through those properties in the
initializer to get validation on
constriction for free. Here we've wrapped
radius_metres, mass_kilograms, orbital or
period seconds, and surface temperature
kelvin in properties setters and getters.
From a robustness standpoint this code is
much better. For example, we can no longer
construct massless planets. Now we get a
value error with a helpful message telling
us that a mass in kilograms with a value
of 0 is not positive. The tradeoff,
though, is that the amount of code is
exploded, and worse, there's a lot of
duplicated code checking that all those
numeric attribute values are non-negative.
Descriptors will ultimately provide a way
out of this, but first we need to do a
little more unraveling of properties to aid our understanding.