Back in Python Beyond the Basics we
introduced property as a function
decorator for property getters. To briefly
recap, a getter method, which encapsulates
direct attribute access, is decorated by
the property decorator, which creates a
property object. The getter function is
bound to an attribute of the property
object called fget, and the original name
of the getter is conceptually rebound to
the property object. The property object
also has an attribute called setter, which
is in fact another decorator. When a
setter method is decorated by the setter
the original property object is modified
to bind and attribute called fset to the
setter method. The property object
effectively aggregates the getter and
setter into a single property object which
behaves like an attribute because it is a
descriptor. Shortly we'll learn how it is
able to appear so attribute like, but
first let's unravel properties a bit more.
Remember that function decorators are just
regular functions which process an
existing function and return a new object,
usually a new function, which wraps the
decorated function. Instead of using
decorator syntax to apply the decorator to
a function we can just define a regular
undecorated function, and then pass the
function to the decorator, rebinding it to
the same or indeed any other name. Given
that decorators are just functions, let's
rework our code to apply property
explicitly using regular function call
syntax, avoiding the special decorator
application syntax using the @ symbol.
When doing this it's important to note
that the property function supports
several arguments for simultaneously
supplying the getter, setter, and deleter
functions, along with a doc string value.
In fact, help property makes this quite
clear. As you can see, we can separately
define our getter and setter functions,
then call the property constructor within
the class definition to produce a class
attribute. Let's use this form in our
Planet class for the numerical attributes.
First we'll remove the property decorator
from the getter functions before removing
the setter decorator from the setter
functions. Now we'll prefix the names of
the getter functions with _get_ and the
names of the setter functions with _set_.
We use single underscore prefixes here
because these are not special methods.
Finally, we create a property object using
the property function. You can think of it
as a constructor call in this context,
passing the pair of getter and setter
functions. Continuing, we need to do the
same for the mass_kilograms property, the
orbital_seconds property, and the
surface_temperature_kelvin property. If
you think this form of property set up is
a retrograde step compared to the
decorator form we'd agree with you.
There's a good reason we introduce
properties as decorators first,
nevertheless, it reinforces the notion
that property is simply a function, which
returns an object called a descriptor
bound to a class attribute. The runtime
behavior of this code hasn't changed at
all. We can still create objects, retrieve
attribute values through properties, and
attempt to set attribute values through
properties with rejection of nonsensical
values. We already know what sort of
operations we can perform with a
descriptor. We can get a value, set a
value, and delete a value. In the case of
property, these getting, setting, and
deleting operations call functions of our
own, which query and manipulate instance
attributes, although in general, the
descriptor operations can be implemented to do almost anything.