We've seen that property is a descriptor,
which wraps three functions. Let's create
a more specialized descriptor useful for
modeling the strictly positive numeric
values in our planet class. Here's a
simple descriptor called Positive. The
descriptor class implements three methods,
which comprise the descriptor protocol;
dunder get, dunder set, and dunder delete,
which are called when we get a value from
a descriptor, set a value through a
descriptor, or delete a value through a
descriptor respectively. In addition, the
positive class implements dunder init to
configure new instances of the descriptor.
Before we look in more detail at each of
these methods let's make use of our new
descriptor to refactor our Planet class.
We remove the setters and getters for
radius_metres and replace the call to the
Property constructor with a call to the
Positive constructor. We do the same for
mass_kilograms, orbital_period_seconds,
and surface_temperature_kelvin. With the
positive descriptor on hand the Planet
class shrinks by a huge amount. At first
sight, this may appear confusing. It looks
like we're assigning to radius_metres
twice, once in the initializer, and once
in the body of the class. In fact, the
call in the body of the class is binding
an instance of a positive descriptor to a
class attribute of the Planet. The call in
dunder init is then apparently assigning
to an instance attribute, although, as
we'll see in a moment, this assignment is
actually invoking a method on the
descriptor object. Allow us to explain the
machinery we have created. Let's start
with an instance of Planet. When we
retrieve an attribute like this, with
pluto. mass_kilograms, the Positive.
dunder get function is called. The
instance argument is set to Pluto, and the
owner argument is set to the object which
owns the descriptor. In this case, the
class Planet. Similarly, our assignments
to the descriptors in the Planet. dunder
init function resolved to calls
effectively equivalent to Positive. dunder
set. Let's review graphically what we have
here. We have a reference, Pluto, which is
bound to an instance of Planet. The dunder
class reference of the instance points to
the Planet class object. The Planet class
object contains four attributes, each of
which references a distinct instance of
the Positive descriptor object. The dunder
class reference of each descriptor object
refers to the Positive class. Notice that
because the descriptor is owned by the
Planet class rather than by the Pluto
instance, we can't just store the value in
the descriptor object. If we did that the
value would be shared between all planet
instances. Instead, we need to somehow
associate the attribute value with the
instance. At first, this seems easy. The
dunder get call is handed a reference to
the instance, Pluto in this case, so why
not just store the value in Pluto's dunder
dict? There's a problem though. Within the
descriptor class, Positive, we have no way
of knowing to which attribute name the
descriptor is bound in the Planet class.
We can distinguish between descriptor
instances in dunder get using the
self-argument, but in Python objects do
not know which names have been bound to
them. This means we have no way of
correlating between descriptor instances
and the descriptor names embedded in the
Planet class. In other words, none of our
descriptor objects know which quantity
they represent. This, in turn, means we
can't store the descriptor value in the
dunder dict of Pluto because we wouldn't
know what dictionary key to use. This
apparent shortcoming of descriptors not
knowing the name of the class attribute to
which they are bound is also evident in
the fact that our value validation error
message in dunder set no longer mentions
the attribute name, a clear regression in
capabilities from what we had earlier.
This is fixable, but the solution will
have to wait until the next module in this
course when we look at meta classes. So
how to associate values with instances?
Let's look at the solution pictorially
first, then we'll reiterate with code. We
use a special collection type from the
Python standard library called
WeakKeyDictionary. This works pretty much
like a regular dictionary, except that it
won't retain value objects, which are
referred to only by the dictionary key
references. We say the references are
weak. A weak key dictionary owned by each
descriptor instance is used to associate
Planet instances with the values of the
quantity represented by that descriptor,
although the descriptor itself doesn't
know which quantity is being represented.
For example, the WeakKeyDictionary shown
here associates Planet instances with
mass_in_kilograms values. A separate
WeakKeyDictionary associates Planet
instances with radius_in_metres values.
Because the dictionary keys are weak
references, if our Planet instance is
destroyed, let's pretend the earth is
vaporized to make way for a hyperspace
bypass, the corresponding entries in all
the WeakKeyDictionaries are also removed.
Now let's switch over to code to see how
it's implemented in practice. A
WeakKeyDictionary instance called
_instance_data is created in the
descriptor initializer, so as we've just
seen, our Planet class indirectly
aggregates four such dictionaries, one in
each of the four descriptors. Within the
dunder set method we associate the
attribute value with the Planet instance
by inserting a mapping from the instance
as key to the attribute as value. As such,
a single dictionary will contain all the
radius_metres values for all planet
instances. Another dictionary will contain
all mass_kilograms values for all Planet
instances, and so on. We're storing the
instance attribute values completely
outside the instances, but in such a way
as we can reliably retrieve them in dunder
get. Just to convince you that all of this
works, we'll show it in action in the
debugger. We'll stop the program in the
initializer for Mars, and step into the
descriptor dunder set function for
technology radius_metres attribute. We can
see that the _instance_data dictionary
already contains the three radii for Mercury, Venus, and Earth.