One aspect of the descriptor protocol we
haven't yet addressed is what happens when
we retrieve a descriptor from a class. As
we've seen, instance attribute retrieval
works fine; however, class attribute
retrieval does not. In such cases, the
instance argument of dunder get will be
set to none, which causes a failure with
the WeakKeyDictionary used for attribute
storage because we cannot create a weak
reference to none. We can use this fact to
detect when a descriptor value is being
retrieved via a class attribute by testing
the instance argument against none. In the
dunder get implementation, when instance
is none we do what seems most natural, and
we turn the descriptor object itself
rather than performing the attribute
lookup. With the revised code we see more
helpful behavior. If you need to query or
manipulate the class which contains the
descriptor object you can get hold of this
through the owner argument of the dunder
get method, which in this case, will
contain a reference to the Planet class.
In many cases, though, you won't need to
use Owner, so you can do what we've done and just ignore it.