You may here the terms data descriptor and
non-data descriptor, but what do they
mean? A non-data descriptor is a
descriptor which implements only the
dunder get method, and so is read only. So
called data descriptors sport both the
dunder get and dunder set methods and are
writable. The distinction is important
because of the precedence of attribute
lookup. Behind the scenes the machinery in
object. dunder getattribute, which is
responsible for all attribute lookup in
Python, transforms a call like this into a
call like this. In fact, a precedence
chain controls attribute lookup according
to the following rules. If an instance is
dunder dict has an entry with the same
name as a data-descriptor the
data-descriptor takes precedence. If an
instance is dunder dict has an entry with
the same name as a non-data descriptor the
dictionary entry takes precedence. These
statements are true, but quite a mouthful.
Another way of looking at it is that
attribute lookup precedes first the data
descriptors, such as properties defined in
the class, then to instance attributes in
dunder dict, and then onto non-data
descriptors in the class again. A simple
experiment should make things clearer.
Here we define a DataDescriptor, a
NonDataDescriptor, and a class which uses
them both called Owner. We'll import all
this into a REPL session. After we've
created an instance of Owner we'll
retrieve the attribute A, set an item in
the instance dictionary with the same
name, and retrieve A again. Since this is
a data descriptor the first rule applies,
and the data descriptor takes precedence
when we call obj. a. Now let's try
attribute b. The first time we access obj.
b there is no entry of the same name in
the instance dictionary, so the
NonDataDescriptor takes precedence. After
we've added a b entry into dunder dict the
second rule applies, and the dictionary
entry takes precedence over the NonDataDescriptor.