Let's summarize. As we've seen, the
descriptor protocol itself is very simple,
which can lead to some very concise and
declarative code, which hugely reduces
duplication. At the same time,
implementing descriptors correctly can be
tricky, and requires careful testing. In
this module we reviewed the built-in
property decorator. We demonstrated how to
create property descriptors without using
decorator syntax by passing property
getters and setters directly to the
property constructor. These reinforce the
notion that properties create objects
called descriptors, which are bound to
class attributes. We showed how to
implement a simple descriptor to perform a
basic attribute validation check by
creating a class that implemented the
descriptor protocol. We explained how
descriptor instances have no knowledge of
to which class attributes they are bound,
so each descriptor instance must store the
instance attributes for all descriptor
owner instances. This can be achieved by
using a WeakKeyDictionary from the Python
standard library Weak Ref module. We
looked at how to know when descriptors are
retrieved from their owning classes rather
than via instances by detecting when the
instance argument to dunder get is set to
none. A natural course of action in such
cases is to return the descriptor instance
itself. We explained the distinction
between data and non-data descriptors, and
how this relates to attribute lookup
precedence. We're not quite done with the
descriptors yet, and in particular, we'd
like descriptor instances to know the name
of the class attributes to which they have
been bound, but to solve that problem we
need sharper tools in the form of Python's
meta classes, which we'll be covering
next. Thanks for watching, and we'll see you in the next module.